A Finding Aid to the Jean Crotti Papers, 1913-1973, bulk 1913-1961, in the Archives of American Art AAA.crotjean
Archives of American Art
Jean Crotti papers
bulk 1913-1961
1913-1973
AAA.crotjean
Archives of American Art
1.7 Linear feet
The scattered papers of French Dada painter Jean Crotti measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1913-1973, with the bulk of the material dated 1913-1961. Found within the papers are autobiographical notes and essays; correspondence with family and colleagues, among them Jean Cocteau, Andre Crotti, Suzanne Duchamp, Marcel Duchamp, Albert Gleizes, Christian a.k.a. Georges Herbiet, Henri Matisse, Francis Picabia, and Jacques Villon; notes and writings by Crotti and others; art work by Crotti and Paul Guillaume; a scrapbook; and additional printed material. Photographs are of Crotti, Suzanne Duchamp, Georges Braque, Pablo Picasso, and other family and friends; and of Crotti's art work. There are audio recordings on phonograph records of three interviews with Crotti and one with Mr. and Mrs. Paul Blancpain.
Crotti, Jean, 1878-1958
Provenance
The Jean Crotti papers were donated in two installments in 1981 by Andr?© Buckles and Alice Buckles Brown, Crotti's great-nephew and great-niece.
Separated Material
Two sketches and a print were also lent by Andr?© Buckles in 1981 for microfilming on reels 2394-2395 and returned. This material is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Alternative Forms Available
This site provides access to the papers of Jean Crotti in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2010, and total 1551 images. Sound recordings have been digitized and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Materials not digitized include an etching plate by Crotti and photographs of artwork. Only the covers and title pages of most published books and exhibition catalogs were scanned.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Jean Crotti (1870-1958) was a Dadist painter who worked primarily in Paris, France and New York. He was married to Suzanne Duchamp, Marcel Duchamp's sister, and friends with notable avant-garde and Dada European and American painters of the period. He is also known for creating the "Gemmail" technique of layering colored glass that produced unique color combinations when illuminated.
Jean Crotti was born April 24, 1878 in Bulle, near Fribourg, Switzerland, the son of a painting contractor. The family moved to Fribourg in 1887.
Beginning in 1898, Crotti struggled with questions of a religious and spiritual nature while at the School of Decorative Arts in Munich. Dissatisfied there, he moved to Paris in 1901, where he spent a year studying at the Acad?©mie Julian under Tony-Robert Fleury and Jules Lefebvre. Still dissatisfied in 1902, he established a small independent studio in the Rue Fontaine.
Crotti exhibited a canvas at the Salon des Ind?©pendants in 1907, and was accepted as a member of the Salon d'Automne in 1909. From 1910 to 1912, he was influenced by Cubism and its offshoot, Orphism.
To escape from wartime Paris in 1914, Crotti and his first wife, Yvonne Chastel, moved to New York City where Crotti had his first solo exhibition at the Bourgeois Gallery. In 1915, Crotti met Francis Picabia and also shared a studio with Marcel Duchamp who was a major influence. Crotti began his Dada period and was included in an exhibition of French paintings at the Montross Gallery in New York, with Duchamp, Albert Gleizes, and Jean Metzinger.
Crotti separated from his first wife, Yvonne Chastel, in 1916 and returned to Paris alone. By 1917, Crotti's marriage had dissolved and he married Suzanne Duchamp in 1919. Crotti met Suzanne Duchamp, also a painter, through his friendship with her brother Marcel Duchamp. During this time, Crotti completed and exhibited paintings associated with the Dada movement. One of his more notable works was entitled Explacatif, bearing the word "Tabu" that expressed Crotti's concepts of mystery and infinity with spiritual overtones.
In 1935 Crotti began to research a new technique using layers of colored glass, referred to as "gemmail." The term is a contraction of "gem" referring to the colored glass and "enamel" referring to the method of affixing the pieces of glass to each other. After much experimentation, an "enamel" fixative was found that would permanently hold the glass pieces in place while still allowing light to shine through all the layers. Several prominent artists including Georges Braque and Pablo Picasso became interested in using this medium. Crotti had the process patented, but in 1955 ceded the rights to Roger Malherbe who adapted it to commercial uses.
Jean Crotti died on January 30, 1958 in Paris, France.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of French Dada painter Jean Crotti measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1913 to 1973, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1913-1961. Among the papers are autobiographical essays, correspondence with friends and family, including many letters from Marcel Duchamp, notes and writings by and about Crotti, printed materials, one scrapbook, drawings by Crotti and others, photographs of Crotti and his family and friends, photographs of artwork, and three audio recordings of interviews with Crotti.
Biographical material consists of autobiographical notes and an autobiographical manuscript Ma Vie.
Correspondence is with family members and colleagues. Correspondents include his brother Andr?©, wife Suzanne Duchamp, and other family members. There are eleven folders of correspondence between Suzanne's brother Marcel Duchamp and the Crotti family. A 1918 letter from Duchamp to Crotti is illustrated by Duchamp. Additional letters to Jean Crotti are from Jean Cocteau, Albert Gleizes, Georges Herbiet a.k.a. "Christian", Henri Matisse, Francis Picabia, and Jacques Villon. Three folders of letters from Georges Herbiet a.k.a. "Christian" include references to Francis Picabia and Germaine Everling and discussions of art criticism and Picabia's role in avant-garde art movements. Herbiet also describes a new painting procedure that he claims to have invented using a product that is impervious to acids, water, oil, or alcohol. There is a single letter from Jean Crotti to Pablo Picasso following their meeting in Cannes in which Crotti discusses a design with spheres and includes a sketch of his idea. There are also single letters to Crotti from Raoul Dufy, Walter Pach, and actor Pierre Renoir.
Notes and writings include poems, a script, and miscellaneous writings by Crotti concerning his art theories including "Tabu" and gemmail. Writings about Crotti are by miscellaneous authors including writers Waldemar George, Andr?© Salmon, and artists Armand Nakache, Am?©d?© Ozenfant, and Michel Seuphor.
Art work includes seven folders of drawings and an etching plate by Crotti, 83 drawings by Paul Guillaume, and portrait drawings of Crotti by Henri Coudour and Francis Picabia.
A scrapbook contains clippings, a letter from Paul Guillaume and a letter to Elizabeth Crotti from a friend describing a 1932 Jean Crotti exhibition in the Balzac Galleries in New York City, and a typescript "Una Collezione a Parigi" by Gino Severini.
Additional printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Crotti and others, reproductions of art work, and books Jean Crotti (1930) and Jean Crotti et la Primaut?© du Spirituel (1959) by Waldemar George.
Photographs are of Crotti, his family, friends, colleagues, and art work by Crotti and by Suzanne Duchamp. Of particular interest are photographs of composer Edgard Var?¨se and his wife Louise with Suzanne Duchamp, Jean Crotti, and art advocate Mary Reynolds in 1924, photographs of Crotti and Georges Braque examining a gemmail art work, and photographs of Crotti and Suzanne Duchamp talking with Pablo Picasso at Cannes and at the home of Bertrande Blancpain in 1957.
Sound recordings include two phonograph records of interviews with Jean Crotti, including topics "Assignment Switzerland" and "Assignment World." A third phonograph record contains an instantatneous disk recording of correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Paul Blancpain as well as an additional interview with Crotti.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1954-1955 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1916-1961 (Box 1; 43 folders)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1924-1958 (Box 1; 27 folders)
Series 4: Art Work, 1913-1925 (Box 1, 3; 12 folders)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1931-1935 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1921-1973 (Box 1, 2, 3; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1920-1957 (Box 2; 25 folders)
Series 8: Sound Recordings, 1955 (Box 3; 1 folder)
Blancpain, Paul; Braque, Georges, 1882-1963; Christian, 1895-1969; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963; Coudour, Henri; Crotti, Andre; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Duchamp, Suzanne, 1889-1963; Dufy, Raoul, 1877-1953; Everling, Germaine; Gleizes, Albert, 1881-1953; Guillaume, Paul, 1891-1934; Matisse, Henri, 1869-1954; Nokache, Armand; Ozenfant, Amédée, 1886-1966; Pach, Walter, 1883-1958; Picabia, Francis, 1879-1953; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973 -- Photographs; Renoir, Pierre, 1885-1952; Reynolds, Mary, 1891-1950; Salmon, André, 1881-1969; Seuphor, Michel, 1901-1999; Severini, Gino, 1883-1966; Varese, Louise; Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965; Villon, Jacques, 1875-1963; Waldemar George, 1893-; Art criticism; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Dadaism; Drawings; Essays; Interviews; Painters--France--Paris; Painters--France--Paris--Interviews; Painting--Technique; Photographs; Poems; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings
- Biographical Material, 1954-1955; Series 1; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of autobiographical notes and an autobiographical manuscript Ma Vie.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Autobiographical Notes, 1954-1955; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Autobiographical Manuscript Ma Vie, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1916-1961; Series 2; (Box 1; 43 folders)
  Correspondence is with family members and colleagues, including his brother Andr?©, wife Suzanne Duchamp, brother-in-law Marcel Duchamp, Jean Cocteau, Albert Gleizes, Georges Herbiet a.k.a. "Christian", Henri Matisse, Francis Picabia (includes a photograph of Picabia), and Jacques Villon.
  There are eleven folders of correspondence with Marcel Duchamp, mostly letters written by Duchamp to Jean Crotti, Suzanne Duchamp, and other family members. A 1918 letter from Duchamp to Crotti is illustrated by Duchamp. Three folders of letters from Georges Herbiet a.k.a. "Christian" include references to Francis Picabia and Germaine Everling and discussions of art criticism and Picabia's role in avant-garde art movements. Herbiet also describes a new painting procedure that he claims to have invented using a product that is impervious to acids, water, oil, or alcohol.
  Also among the correspondence is one letter to Pablo Picasso discussing a design with spheres and a sketch, and single letters from Raoul Dufy, Walter Pach, actor Pierre Renoir, and Henri Matisse. The letter from Matisse discusses the design of a palette.
  - Letters from Georges Herbiet a.k.a. "Christian" to Jean Crotti, 1922-1929; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Letters from Jean Cocteau to Jean Crotti, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Jean Crotti to Andr?©, Marie, and Lysbeth Crotti, undated, 1940-1957; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Letter from Jean Crotti to Marcel Duchamp, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Jean Crotti to Suzanne Duchamp, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Jean Crotti to Pablo Picasso, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Jean Crotti to Miscellaneous Colleagues, 1936-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Pierre De Massot to Jean Crotti, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters from Roland Dorgeles to Jean Crotti, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters from Marcel Duchamp to Jean Crotti, Yvonne Crotti, and Suzanne Duchamp, 1916-1961, undated (folder 21 includes an illustrated letter from Duchamp.); (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-27)
  - Letter from Raoul Dufy to Jean Crotti, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters from Waldemar George to Jean Crotti, 1925-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters from Albert Gleizes to Jean Crotti, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Henri Matisse to Jean Crotti, 1923-1936 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter from Walter Pach to Jean Crotti, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters from Cl?©ment Pansaers to Jean Crotti, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letters from Francis Picabia to Jan Crotti (2 folders), 1922-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Letter from Pierre Renoir to Jean Crotti, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters from Andr?© Salmon to Jean Crotti, 1922-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters from Paul Signac to Jean Crotti, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters from L. Stoppela?©re Jean Crotti, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters from Jean Villern (?) to Jean Crotti, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters from Jacques Villon to Jean Crotti and Suzanne Duchamp, 1918-1961, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - Letters from Miscellaneous Correspondents to Jean Crotti, 1917-1955, undated; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-46)
- Notes and Writings, 1924-1958; Series 3; (Box 1; 27 folders)
  Notes and writings include poems, a script, and miscellaneous writings by Crotti concerning his art theories. Miscellaneous writings by others are primarily about Crotti.
  - Lists of Art Work, 1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1937-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Poems by Jean Crotti, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Script Porte Sans Issue, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Notebook and Writings Concerning Tabu, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
  - Miscellaneous Writings by Jean Crotti, 1934-1957, undated; (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 53-60)
  - Manuscript about Jean Crotti by Jean Bouret; Typescript about Jean Crotti by Jean Cassou, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Typescript about Jean Crotti by Raymond Cogniat, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Writings about Jean Crotti by Waldemar George, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Writings about Jean Crotti by Georges-Armand Masson; Typescripts about Jean Crotti by Jean-Daniel Maublanc, 1936-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Typescript "Rapport de la Commission des F?ªtes de la Soci?©t?© des Amateurs d'Art" by Ren?© Idzkowski, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Manuscripts about Jean Crotti by Claude M?©ran, 1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Typescript about Jean Crotti by Armand Nakache, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Typescript about Jean Crotti by Am?©d?© Ozenfant, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Writings about Jean Crotti by Andr?© Salmon, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Typescript about Jean Crotti by Michel Seuphor, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Writings about Jean Crotti by Miscellaneous Authors, 1928-1958, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 71-73)
- Art Work, 1913-1925; Series 4; (Box 1, 3; 12 folders)
  Art work consists of drawings by Crotti and others including a portrait of Crotti by Francis Picabia, and drawings by paul Guillaume. Also included is an etching plate created by Crotti.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Items not digitized include the etching plate and a folder of photographs of works of art loaned by Crotti to the Archives of American Art for microfilming.
  - Drawings by Jean Crotti, 1913, undated; (7 folders; Oversized Material also housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 74-80)
    partially scanned
  - Etching Plate by Jean Crotti, undated; (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Drawing of Jean Crotti by Henri Coudour, undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Drawing by Paul Guillaume, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Drawing of Jean Crotti by Francis Picabia, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Three Oversized Drawings by Jean Crotti, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    (scanned with Box 1, Folder 77)
- Scrapbook, 1931-1935; Series 5; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  The scrapbook contains clippings, a letter from Paul Guillaume and a letter to Elizabeth Crotti from a friend describing a 1932 Jean Crotti exhibition in the Balzac Galleries in New York City, and a typescript by Gino Severini.
  - Scrapbook, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Printed Material, 1921-1973; Series 6; (Box 1-3; 0.5 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Crotti and others, reproductions of art work, and books about Crotti.
  This series has been partially scanned. Items not scanned include a folder of reproductions of works of art by Crotti. Also, published books and catalogs of which only the covers and title pages are scanned.
  - Clippings, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Clippings, 1928; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 87-89)
  - Clippings, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Clippings, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Clippings, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Clippings, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Clippings, 1939; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 94-95)
  - Clippings, 1942; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 96-98)
  - Clippings, 1943; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 99-100)
  - Clippings, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Clippings, 1945; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 102-103)
  - Clippings, 1946; (2 folders; Oversized Material also housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 104-105)
  - Clippings, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Clippings, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Clippings, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Clippings, 1950; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 109-110)
  - Clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Clippings, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 115-116)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    (partially scanned)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 120-121)
    (partially scanned; 2 folders)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (partially scanned; Oversized Material also housed in Box 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reproductions of Art Work, undated; (not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book Jean Crotti by Waldemar George, 1930; (not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book Jean Crotti et la Primaut?© du Spirituel by Waldemar George, 1959; (not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1937-1956, undated; (2 folders; Oversized Material also housed in Box 3) (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - An Oversized Clipping, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    (scanned with Box 1, Folder 104)
  - An Oversized Exhibition Announcement Poster, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    (scanned with Box 2, Folder 3)
  - An Oversized Galley Proof Sheet of Illustrations about French Aviation, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    (scanned with Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1920-1957; Series 7; (Box 2; 25 folders)
  Photographs are of Crotti, his family, friends, and colleagues including Bertrande Blancpain, Georges Braque examining a gemmail art work, Suzanne Duchamp, Pablo Picasso, Mary Reynolds, composer Edgard Var?¨se, and Jacques Villon. There are also photographs of art work by Crotti and by Suzanne Duchamp.
  This bulk of this series has been scanned. Photographs of works of art have not been scanned.
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti, 1922-1957, undated; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Photographs of Suzanne Duchamp, 1933-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti with Friends and Colleagues, 1920-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti on Bateau Moineau, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti with Georges Braque, Examining a Gemmail Art Work, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti and Suzanne Duchamp with Pablo Picasso and Bertrande Blancpain, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Jean Crotti with Pablo Picasso at Palais du Festival in Cannes, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of an Unidentified Exhibition Installation, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Salon des Independants Exhibition Installation, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of Art Work by Jean Crotti, undated; (not scanned; 9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-30)
  - Photographs of Art Work by Suzanne Duchamp, undated; (not scanned; 2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Photograph of Art Work by Camille Pisarro, undated; (not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Photograph of Lake Michigan, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Sound Recordings, 1955; Series 8; (Box 3; 1 folder)
  Sound recordings include two phonograph records of interviews with Jean Crotti, including topics "Assignment Switzerland" and "Assignment World." A third phonograph record is an instantaneous recording of correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Paul Blancpain and Crotti.
  - Phonograph Recordings of Interviews with Jean Crotti and recorded correspondence with Mr. and Mrs. Paul Blancpain, 1955, undated; 3 Sound discs (lacquer) (Box 3)
    These recordings have been digitized for research access.